AUTHOR: HITOSHI IWAAKI
AUTOR: HITOSHI IWAAKI
THE SUN ALSO RISES
SŁOŃCE ZNOWU WSTANIE
I pierced the heart.
Przebiłam serce.
Your human host died instantly.
Twój gospodarz umarł od razu.
You'll follow in a matter of minutes.
Ty umrzesz za parę minut.
Accept your fate as one who failed to seize the head.
Pogódź się z losem tego, który nie przejął mózgu.
There's no time to lose.
Muszę się spieszyć.
A direct hit to the heart cannot be repaired in mere minutes.
Serca po takim ciosie nie naprawi się w kilka minut.
Yet, if I do nothing, Shinichi's brain will die.
Jeśli nic nie zrobię, mózg Shinichiego umrze.
Which means…
A to znaczy…
my only option is to merge myself with his heart.
że muszę się połączyć z jego sercem.
While I seal the hole in his heart,
Gdy zaszyję dziurę w sercu,
I must maintain his heart function as well as circulate blood within myself.
muszę utrzymać jego funkcje i przetaczać krew przez siebie.
She seems to have successfully relocated to her current host's head,
Ona przeniosła się do nowego gospodarza.
but what I am about to embark on is a far riskier venture.
Ja zrobię coś bardziej ryzykownego.
All right. I think I can make this work.
Dobrze. Chyba się uda.
But I cannot expect spontaneous recovery.
Ale szybko nie wyzdrowieje.
I should gradually recruit cells from all over his body
Muszę zaangażować komórki z całego ciała,
to augment the healing of his wound.
żeby wspomóc leczenie rany.
At the same time, I will gradually return to his right hand
A ja powoli wrócę do jego ręki
through his bloodstream.
przez krwiobieg.
What?
Co?
Izumi-kun's absent again today?
Dzisiaj też nie ma Izumi-kuna?
Yeah.
Tak.
Our homeroom teacher tried calling his home,
Wychowawca dzwonił do domu,
but no one's picking up.
ale nikt nie odbiera.
That worries me.
Martwię się.
-Want to swing by on our way home? -Sure.
- Wstąpimy do niego? - Dobrze.
-Oh, but I don't know his address. -I do.
- Nie wiem, gdzie mieszka. - Ja wiem.
I went home with Izumi-kun the other day.
Byłam u niego niedawno.
-What? -Hey!
- Co? - Hej!
Since when are you and Izumi-kun a thing?
Od kiedy ty i Izumi-kun jesteście parą?
No! That's not it.
Nie! To nie tak!
It's not? Then, what is it?
Nie? To jak?
It's none of your business, Akiho!
Nie twoja sprawa, Akiho!
Don't butt in!
Pilnuj swojego nosa!
Why not? Come on!
Dlaczego? Powiedz!
So, is Izumi dating Murano?
Izumi jest z Murano?
Shut up!
Zamknij się!
Come on. Tell me.
No weź, powiedz mi.
Oh, drop it, Akiho.
Daj już spokój, Akiho.
Sugar, huh.
Cukier.
The hole's been sealed.
Rana się zabliźniła.
It looks more like it's been fused shut than sewn up.
Ale jest zrośnięta, a nie zszyta.
Migi?
Migi?
Did Migi heal me?
On mnie uleczył?
S…
Czyli…
So, it wasn't…
Czyli to nie był…
a dream.
sen.
Hello?
Halo.
Oh, we finally got a hold of you. I'm calling from Sakurazaki Hospital.
W końcu ktoś odebrał. Dzwonię ze szpitala w Sakurazaki.
Is this where Izumi Kazuyuki-san lives?
Dodzwoniłam się do domu Izumi Kazuyuki-sana?
Yes.
Tak.
Did something happen to Dad?
Coś się stało tacie?
Yes, but he is fine.
Tak, ale już wszystko w porządku.
He's asleep right now,
Teraz śpi.
but his life is not in any danger.
Jego życie nie jest już zagrożone.
So, when you come to visit, can you bring things,
Może pan przynieść jego rzeczy.
like clothes and--
Ubrania i…
I'll come right away!
Już tam jadę!
Izumi-kun?
Izumi-kun?
Oh…
Ja…
I just came by because you haven't been at school.
Przyszłam, bo nie było cię w szkole.
You'd mentioned that your parents were away traveling, too,
Mówiłeś, że twoi rodzice wyjechali.
so I thought maybe you've been at home sick and alone.
Pomyślałam, że czujesz się samotny.
Dad got hurt on his trip.
Tata miał wypadek podczas wycieczki.
What?
Co?
Then your mom must be stuck dealing with it alone.
Twojej mamie pewnie jest ciężko.
I won't be back at school for a while.
Przez jakiś czas nie będzie mnie w szkole.
Izumi-kun.
Izumi-kun.
Shinichi-kun!
Shinichi-kun!
You'll come back, right?
Wrócę tutaj, dobrze?
I'll kill her!
Zabiję ją!
Dad saw her in that form before he ran away.
Tata widział ją pod tą postacią, zanim uciekł.
That's why she looked up our address and came all the way here.
Dlatego odszukała nasz adres i tu przyszła.
That man has not returned?
Ten mężczyzna nie wrócił?
How did she find our address?
Skąd wzięła nasz adres?
In their luggage or at their hotel?
Z ich bagażu w hotelu?
I bet she'll eventually figure out which hospital Dad's in, too.
Pewnie się dowie, w którym szpitalu leży tata.
I have to hurry. Hurry.
Muszę się pospieszyć.
Excuse me.
Przepraszam.
Are you okay?
Wszystko w porządku?
You seem really troubled.
Wyglądasz na zmartwionego.
Are you from Sakurazaki?
Jesteś z Sakurazaki?
Huh? Yeah.
Co? Tak.
Then you know where Sakurazaki Hospital is, right?
Wiesz, gdzie jest szpital w Sakurazaki?
Oh, yeah.
Wiem doskonale.
So it was on the 18th, at dusk, when your wife was murdered?
Czyli wieczorem osiemnastego pana żona została zamordowana?
Yes.
Tak.
Has my wife's body been found?
Znaleziono jej ciało?
Izumi-san.
Izumi-san.
Your wife is alive.
Pana żona żyje.
What?
Co?
On the 18th, the day you fell into the sea,
Osiemnastego, gdy wpadł pan do morza,
your wife returned alone to the hotel after 9:00 p.m.
pana żona o 21 wróciła do hotelu.
That's impossible!
To niemożliwe!
She spoke with the front desk staff,
Rozmawiała z recepcją.
saying you had to leave early on urgent business,
Powiedziała, że musiał pan wyjechać, a ona zostanie na jeszcze jedną noc.
Then she checked out the next morning.
Rano się wymeldowała.
No. That's not possible.
Nie. To niemożliwe.
It was an imposter.
To oszustka.
But the staff saw the burn mark on Nobuko-san's right arm,
Obsługa widziała bliznę na ręce pani Nobuko.
and they're sure that's who they saw.
Są pewni, że to była ona.
Izumi-san.
Izumi-san.
I believe your deep psychological shock is causing
Myślę, że doznał pan szoku
the reality you saw before the fall and the nightmare you had after the fall
i to, co widział pan przed upadkiem, miesza się panu
to become jumbled together.
z koszmarem, który się panu śnił.
That was no nightmare.
To nie był koszmar.
I know it wasn't!
Wiem, że nie!
It's here.
To tutaj.
SAKURAZAKI HOSPITAL
SZPITAL W SAKURAZAKI
Thank you.
Dziękuję.
Bye!
Pa!
Yes, he's down that way.
Tak, proszę iść tam.
Dad!
Tato!
Shinichi.
Shinichi.
Da…
Tato…
I'm sorry I made you worry.
Przepraszam, że się martwiłeś.
Mom is…
Mama jest…
It hurts so much.
Bardzo boli.
I can barely speak from the grief, yet I have no tears.
Z rozpaczy ledwo mówię, ale nie potrafię uronić łzy.
Are you okay, Shinichi?
Nic ci nie jest, Shinichi?
Mom's…
Mama…
Shinichi.
Shinichi.
About Mom.
Co do mamy.
She got caught up in some accident and we don't know where she is.
Miała wypadek i nie wiemy, gdzie jest.
What?
Co?
Dad.
Tato.
You saw, didn't you?
Widziałeś to, prawda?
Saw what?
Co?
You mean…
Czyli…
Yeah.
Tak.
I apparently had a nightmare because I hit my head.
Mówią, że śnił mi się koszmar, bo uderzyłem się w głowę.
A nightmare?
Koszmar?
That's a lie!
To kłamstwo!
I've asked the police to look for her.
Kazałem policji jej poszukać.
I'll need to stay here for a while yet, but it's nothing serious.
Muszę zostać w szpitalu, ale to nic poważnego.
What are you saying?
O czym ty mówisz?
How can you say all this, Dad?
Jak możesz tak mówić?
Shinichi, did something happen at home?
Shinichi, coś się wydarzyło w domu?
You know something happened!
Wiesz, że tak!
Mom was murdered!
Mama została zamordowana!
By a monster!
Przez potwora!
I said that kind of nonsense on the phone?
Mówiłem takie bzdury przez telefon?
Sorry!
Przepraszam!
I'm so sorry!
Bardzo przepraszam!
I was wrong!
Pomyliłem się.
What?
Co?
Does he really think he dreamed it all up?
Naprawdę myśli, że to mu się śniło?
Shinichi, I'm going to be okay.
Shinichi, wyjdę z tego.
I want you to take it easy for two or three days, then go back home.
Odpocznę dwa czy trzy dni i wrócę do domu.
I know it's tough,
Jest ciężko,
but hang in there for just a little longer.
ale wytrzymaj jeszcze chwilę.
If you have any problems, go to your uncle in Chiba--
Jeśli coś się stanie, pojedź do wujka w Chibie…
Dad, I need to talk to you about something.
Tato, muszę ci coś powiedzieć.
It's about Mom and the monster--
Chodzi o mamę i potwora…
Shinichi!
Shinichi!
Please. I can't talk about that right now.
Proszę. Nie chcę teraz o tym rozmawiać.
Dad. He's crying.
Tata płacze.
So he does know.
Czyli wie.
He knows Mom's dead.
Wie, że mama nie żyje.
I wish I could tell him what the monster actually is!
Chciałbym mu powiedzieć, czym jest ten potwór!
Tell him what kind of creature killed Mom!
Jaki stwór zabił mamę!
If only Migi was a true ally to humanity!
Gdyby tylko Migi był prawdziwym sojusznikiem ludzkości!
I brought some clothes.
Przyniosłem ci ubrania.
Shinichi, where are you going to stay?
Shinichi, gdzie się zatrzymasz?
I'll stay here.
Tutaj.
But you can't get a good night's rest here.
Tutaj się nie wyśpisz.
There's supposedly a hotel near the beach,
Niedaleko plaży jest hotel.
so you should go stay there.
Tam się zatrzymaj.
A hospital.
Szpital.
Wait, Migi's asleep.
Chwila, Migi śpi.
Maybe this is my chance to reveal him.
Może mam szansę go ujawnić.
No. Now isn't the time!
Nie. Teraz to zła pora!
I need his abilities to both find and fight the enemy!
Musi mi pomóc odnaleźć wroga i z nim walczyć.
It's pathetic, but I have no choice but to rely on him right now!
To żałosne, ale muszę na nim polegać!
What? Sakurazaki Hotel's that far from here?
Co? Hotel jest tak daleko?
It's not that far.
To nie tak daleko.
It's only about 300 meters away.
Tylko 300 metrów stąd.
Three hundred meters.
Trzysta metrów.
That's right on the edge of Migi's ability to detect the enemy.
To granica, z której Migi może wyczuć wroga.
It'll be too late if we detect her as she shows up at the hospital.
Będzie za późno, jeśli wyczujemy ją, gdy będzie w szpitalu.
INN NAMIKI 50 M DOWN THE HILL
PENSJONAT NAMIKI 50 METRÓW
It's right behind the hospital.
Jest tuż za szpitalem.
This is perfect.
Idealnie.
Excuse me.
Przepraszam.
Will it be just you staying here?
Zatrzymasz się u nas?
Oh, you're…
Jesteś…
Mom!
Mamo!
We have a guest!
Mamy gościa!
SAKURAZAKI HOSPITAL
SZPITAL W SAKURAZAKI
Dad must've seen Mom get killed.
Tata pewnie widział śmierć mamy.
I'll eventually have to tell him everything I know.
Kiedyś muszę mu powiedzieć wszystko, co wiem.
But right now, I have to keep Dad alive and avenge Mom!
Ale teraz muszę go bronić i pomścić mamę!
Your meal's ready for you downstairs.
Jedzenie jest gotowe.
Okay.
Dobrze.
I can easily sense people.
Z łatwością wyczuwam ludzi.
Are the walls that thin, or did my hearing improve?
Te ściany są takie cienkie czy poprawił mi się słuch?
INN NAMIKI
PENSJONAT NAMIKI
Shinichi.
Shinichi.
I thought about keeping it to myself, but I decided to tell you.
Chciałem zachować to dla siebie, ale postanowiłem ci powiedzieć.
It's important.
To ważne.
Your feelings towards your family are quite strong.
Darzysz swoją rodzinę ogromnym uczuciem.
In comparison, your feelings toward me are not as…
W porównaniu z uczuciami do mnie…
No, rather, I know you think of me more as a nuisance.
Wiem, że uznajesz mnie za kłopot.
While we are allies,
Jesteśmy sojusznikami,
we may also be enemies who belong to two different species.
ale możemy być wrogami z dwóch różnych gatunków.
What's your point?
Do czego zmierzasz?
The day I repaired your damaged body,
Gdy naprawiłem twoje zniszczone ciało,
I also underwent change during the process.
również przeszedłem przemianę.
Change?
Przemianę?
I now have a weakness.
Teraz mam słabość.
A weakness that others of my kind do not have.
Inni z mojego gatunku jej nie mają.
For about four hours a day, I fall asleep.
Śpię cztery godziny dziennie.
That's it?
I tyle?
You've slept before.
Wcześniej też spałeś.
It's not the same.
To nie to samo.
Until now, even if I was asleep, the slightest thing would wake me up.
Do tej pory, gdy spałem, budziła mnie nawet najmniejsza rzecz.
For example, if you were surprised, if your breathing became uneven,
Gdy byłeś zaskoczony i miałeś nierówny oddech
or if one of my kind showed up 300 meters away.
albo gdy ktoś z mojego gatunku pojawił się 300 metrów od nas.
One of your kind.
Jeden z twoich.
That's right.
Zgadza się.
But now, I'm unable to detect any of that when I'm asleep.
Ale teraz tego nie czuję, gdy śpię.
So, should an enemy appear during those four hours,
Jeśli wróg pojawi się w ciągu tych czterech godzin,
it'd mean the end for us both.
to będzie po nas.
I had to detach from your right arm
Musiałem na długo rozłączyć się z twoją prawą ręką,
My physiology was slightly altered as a result.
Przez to się trochę zmieniłem.
Why didn't you tell me something that important?
Dlaczego nie powiedziałeś mi czegoś tak ważnego?
It appears you harbor strong animosity toward me
Jesteś wobec mnie wrogi,
now that one of my kind has killed your mother.
bo jeden z moich zabił twoją mamę.
It is dangerous to tell an enemy about one's weakness.
Wrogowi nie można mówić o swoich słabościach.
That's why I didn't tell you until now.
Dlatego wcześniej nie powiedziałem.
But I have decided that continuing to keep you in the dark
Ale uznałem, że jeśli nie będziesz wiedział,
would be even more dangerous.
będzie to bardziej niebezpieczne.
Do you understand now?
Teraz rozumiesz?
I don't think of you as an enemy anymore, Migi.
Nie uważam cię za wroga.
You saved my life.
Ocaliłeś mi życie.
That is not entirely precise.
To nie do końca prawda.
Your life sustains my life as well.
Twoje życie podtrzymuje moje.
Morning!
Dzień dobry!
Good morning.
Dzień dobry.
Huh? Your color looks better today.
Lepiej dzisiaj wyglądasz.
You were more haggard yesterday.
Wczoraj byłeś bardziej zmizerniały.
I guess you got a good night's rest.
Chyba dobrze spałeś.
SAKURAZAKI HOSPITAL
SZPITAL W SAKURAZAKI
Oh, thanks.
Dziękuję.
It must've been a while since you last read the paper.
Dawno nie czytałeś gazety.
Yeah.
Tak.
I lost both my tablet and my cell when I fell into the sea.
Gdy wpadłem do morza, straciłem tablet i telefon.
We'll have to replace them once we get home.
Kupimy ci nowe, gdy wrócimy do domu.
Yeah.
Jasne.
What's your plan?
Co planujesz?
I'll stay here a while longer and see how things go.
Zostanę tu dłużej i zobaczę, co będzie.
While Migi is in deep sleep,
Migi mocno śpi,
I have to use my own eyes to keep watch.
więc sam muszę obserwować.
When possible,
Migi może spać w środku dnia, gdy wokół jest dużo ludzi,
and the risk of attack is small.
a szansa na atak jest mała.
What would be her approach?
Co ona kombinuje?
Migi told me not to fight until he was awake,
Migi zabronił mi walczyć, gdy śpi,
but I won't have a choice if she suddenly comes at me.
ale nie będę miał wyjścia, gdy ona się pojawi.
Besides, I could never run away from Mom's killer!
Poza tym nie ucieknę przed mordercą mamy!
Hello.
Cześć.
Hey. Makiko-chan, right?
Cześć. Makiko-chan, tak?
You can call me Maki.
Mów mi „Maki”.
Were you sitting here all this time?
Cały czas tutaj siedzisz?
Are you that worried about your dad?
Tak bardzo martwisz się o tatę?
I guess.
Chyba tak.
It's not like there's much else to do.
Nie mam nic innego do roboty.
I see.
Rozumiem.
Hey, do you have a girlfriend?
Masz dziewczynę?
Shinichi! We have company!
Shinichi! Mamy towarzystwo!
It's just about 300 meters away, in the direction of the beach.
Jest 300 metrów stąd w stronę plaży.
She's here!
Jest tu!
Maki-chan! Which road leads to the beach?
Jak dojdę na plażę?
What?
Na plażę?
You can just keep going on the road you take to my place--
Idź jak do mojego domu…
Hey, wait!
Poczekaj!
But if you stay on that road, you'll hit a seawall!
Dalej będzie falochron!
Hey!
Hej!
Wait!
Poczekaj!
He's so fast!
Ale jest szybki!
Shinichi, I need to confirm.
Shinichi, muszę potwierdzić.
Confirm what?
Co?
Is it acceptable to kill her?
Można ją zabić?
Yes!
Tak!
Just thinking about how she's still out loose in the world
Gdy myślę, że chodzi sobie po świecie,
makes my blood boil!
krew się we mnie gotuje!
I told you to wait,
Kazałam ci poczekać.
but you just up and ran off.
Ale tak szybko pobiegłeś.
To get to the beach, you have to circle around that way--
Żeby dojść na plażę, musisz obejść…
Seriously?
Serio?
Something just went out of sight at the other end.
Coś zniknęło na końcu falochronu.
That's her!
To ona!
Shinichi, there's another thing I need to tell you.
Shinichi, muszę ci coś jeszcze powiedzieć.
It's about you.
O tobie.
I've only just become certain of it myself, but--
Właśnie się upewniłem…
Save it for later!
Powiesz mi później!
I won't let you get away! I'll make you pay!
Nie dam ci uciec. Zapłacisz za to!
You'll pay for killing Mom!
Zapłacisz za zabicie mamy!
Don't you move!
Nie ruszaj się!
Next time, "Dark Night's Passing."
Następny odcinek: „Ciemna noc przeminie”.